welcome meditating with john vervecki we
live
every weekday morning at 9 30 a.m with
mondays alternating between a new lesson
called the dharma day
and a review of a whole ecology of
practices called
day if you're joining us for the first
time you're you're very welcome
for previous lessons and see the
description in this video
i recommend you go immediately and do
lesson one
and then do two you know one or two
lessons
every week and you you will very quickly
integrate with us
please continue to keep meeting with us
uh that will help you get
involved and develop the practice in
depth
i would ask you all to please like this
uh video stream to increase its
uh visibility in the youtube algorithm
so i can help as many as people as
possible with this work
at the end of every session there are uh
there's a q a period uh please limit the
questions at that time to the
anything from the entire ecology of
practices uh for more general questions
um we have a live stream on youtube
every third friday of the month that'll
be august 21st of this month
um at 3 p.m eastern and
i welcome as many of you uh as can
possibly make it because i think it's a
very
rich and rewarding experience normally
when you come in
uh i'm sitting um on my mat in my my
zafu my
meditation pillow but today we're doing
a final review
of an aspect of the walking meditation
the brush needs from tai chi chuang i'm
just going to review it one more time
giving special emphasis uh to the arms
and then
we'll move into the sitted practice okay
so
again when i'm doing this what i'm going
to do is i'm going to
put my as always like when i start the
walking i turn my right foot 45 degrees
here's my line here's 90
45 degrees but when i'm going to add in
the arms
i step onto this part of my left foot
right
right behind the toes and i have a bend
in my knee
right and then what i'm going to do i'm
going to turn my hips 45
and as i do i'll do side on so you can
see this best
what happens is this arm turns notice i
don't straighten it i keep it bent
right it's this is tongue again that
sort of
almost like your arms are filled with
water flowing through them
they're flexible but they're not limp
and they're not locked
okay so pump and so when i'm turning
turning this part the hard part of my
arm and the knife edge of my hand out
i'm protecting here my my liver my lungs
and my heart so there's a full body
block
that's my what's my left hand is doing
my right hand is coming
up it's spiraling up so it's palm
towards me with this finger the middle
finger
just around the tip of just above the
tip of my nose but in line with the tip
of my nose
so that looks like this
and notice i'm turning my hips
okay okay so once i do this then i start
the tai chi walk
walking right the meditative walking
right remember heel to toe
and as my heel goes down remember i'm
straightening my hips and what that
straightening my hips does
is it moves this hand past my knee
it's called brush knee and when i finish
the move my hand comes beside my thigh
here
and as if i'm touching a board like this
this hand
is like a curved l so it doesn't go on
the diagonal it doesn't go like this
it spirals into the center that nose to
navel
line spirals into the center and then
down and notice how i keep a deep bend
in my arm i am not
this is very mistaken and this is what
i'm doing
okay so what does that look like i'm
turning turning turning
stepping straightening the hips brushing
the knee
spiraling down the center coming in
okay so remembering in tai chi walking
meditative walking
i set my weight back and my i come up
onto my left heel as i do that my hands
my palms rotate in and then as i
turn right remember i do this i align
everything my knee remember aligning the
knees in my
left knee coming into place my hands are
aligned like this
okay keep this hand like
when i say a line there don't be
directly below it hold slightly ahead of
it
so slightly this way okay so like this
and then now this is the difficult part
i'm going to try and do it as slowly as
possible
remember what i do is i do this with my
weight i bring my weight i turn all of
my weight onto my left leg no weight
going into my
right heel and that brings up my right
foot now as i'm doing that
these hands are switching so that this
is now like this and then this is the
full body block here
okay so like this right
i'm aligned i turn
okay my line i turn
okay i'm aligned i turn
and then i brush the knee on this side i
brush the knee on this side
i brush the knee on this side okay
so let's say i brush my knee now that's
the name of the move
brush knees okay
so i think like i said i'll do it first
this way
i got the full camera i want to turn i
got a brush knee
and i want to turn so let's just do the
footwork again up
pivot no weight yet shift weight from
here to here pivot more
let this foot slide a bit let the right
foot slide a bit
and then up and over okay so
but i'm doing the first part of the of
the weight shift with the footwork
i'm spiraling this down and i'm
spiraling this up what i'm doing is i'm
actually
storing energy in the elasticity of my
tissues
right so what when you when the martial
arts you're learning to coordinate not
just the large piston muscles you're
learning to coordinate all the small
that's why you're doing all this
spiraling you're first of all you're
coordinating all the control muscles and
getting it's like a laser
you know ambient light the light bounces
off in all directions in the laser
it's reflected right so that it all
becomes coherent and it moves
in a unified pattern and so i'm trying
to get all the muscles
to have that coherence to them that's
part of what qi is
and then also i'm storing energy in the
elasticity of the tissue so it's not
just
muc so like if i'm striking someone
right
when i strike it's not just piston
muscles
it's also the small control muscles and
it's also the elasticity of the tissue
and it's the weight shift and i'm
getting everything coherent into one
strike
okay hopefully you'll never use this for
fighting
but the idea is you understand the
function it helps you to do the form
correctly
okay so i'm like this i rotate
and then now right shift from
right this leg to this leg i start to
unwrap my hands
over and now you see i'm ready i'm ready
for a brushing
what would that look like on this side
same thing wrapping
starting to unwrap over
brush me
wrapping getting into place
see this starting to unwrap right here
right here
over brush knee
okay i think this is better right here
right wrapping and then
start to unwrap and that gets this hand
down into place the lower hand
this is now right in front of my nose
ready to go and boom
so remember whenever i'm so
inhale because i'm getting everything
ready i'm drawing everything in this is
the end part
and then yang exhale and then in
right and then exhale then in
and then exhale
so you're meditating on the flow of your
breath you're meditating on your
center your root
obviously your flow and now the final
part your right the final part is this
and this is a word that should not be
translated because whenever it's
mistranslated it
gives people all kinds of crazy
metaphysical ideas
but this is the this is the key that the
chi or the key
if you she is chinese key is japanese
it's that
sense of laser-like coherence
but it's it's simultaneously
an awareness of
like it's an intelligent flowing
living coherence that's sort of the
musicality
of your own perspectival and
participatory awareness
of your body in movement
so i hope that's helpful and i'm just
going to go off camera
and jason's going to adjust the camera
i'm going to get my mat
and my pillow and we will move into the
seated practice
okay everyone can you please get
yourself into position
and such bones on do not disturb
as always we will begin uh with some
chanting
and then we'll go into a silent sit um
and then we'll have our time to answer
uh some questions we'll begin when i say
begin
begin oh
one
[Music]
oh
on
[Music]
one
on
[Music]
one
um
on
one
begin your silence set
oh
now
uh
foreign
huh
[Music]
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition character
and communitas perhaps by reciting the
five promises to yourself
oh
okay we have time for a couple questions
uh the first is from jonas do we need to
prepare
anything from the wisdom of haiti before
next monday
yes uh please read the first three
chapters
that's 70 pages and consider
uh taking up uh over the weekend uh
maybe a couple of the initial practices
on self-examination et cetera you know
what those are when you see them
um and that way we can have a bit of
momentum going
uh when we have our uh day on monday
so manual post thank you for waiting and
being patient manual and giving me
feedback so i can hopefully give you a
better answer
i'll read through the whole thing um
i have the idea that in my youth i used
to be fairly a barely
visual thinker i've had a brain injury
i'm sorry to hear that by the way
pressure due to inflammation that i
associate with the loss of my ability to
access visual memories thinking
the same is true for the auditory i'm
sorry to hear that
um i have some sense of what it is to
lose
the veneers has cost me my hearing in my
my left ear
um so i have some sense of what that's
like i think there's value in
cultivating these skills to proclaim
some of what i've lost
i've been able to have limited access
after intense concentration
no doubt um so the veins plasticity
its capacity to rewire
and make use of other areas
we're going to talk about this a little
bit more on monday
it is is very significant
recently during meditation i've been
developing my ability to perceive and
influence really limited visual and also
some auditory experience after intense
concentration
during recent meditation i've been
developing my ability to perceive and
influence really limited visual and also
some auditory experience
so um this makes great sense um so
we know that meditators
what seems to happen and we'll talk a
lot about this on monday when we talk
about savory
right there is a bottom-up aspect of
taking information in from the world
and then a top-down inhibition that
screens off a lot of that and tries to
find the familiar patterns what
meditation does
is it relaxes that top-down influence
and opens it up makes it more flexible
so more of the bottom up influence comes
up
and this is what what i mean when i say
you can use imagination which is the top
down to make this top down more flexible
in order to train perception the more
bottom up
and so meditation uh actually tends to
create synesthesia in people
uh this is when you s you have a color
experience that you see
colors in sound or all right or you
taste shapes right um and so we know
that meditation can in fact
do that kind of rewiring and because the
way it probably functions
i've had experience when i took my first
dose of an ssri
um is that i perhaps there's some
depression associated with the chronic
loss
uh where i unleashed an uncontrollable
flow of thoughts
so with with this context my question is
twofold so that's a very
excellent explication of the context
manual i want to ask for methods of
cultivation of the visual and auditory
and if there is a threat to engaging and
not fully integrated part of the brain
and this might grow out of control
okay so first of all
and this this is not delivered this is
just how it
uh fell together when uh the thing i'm
going to be teaching you
on monday as part of extended um
epicureanism the the savoring
of of simple experience will really help
get that better relationship between the
bottom-up
perception and the top-down uh
pre-hending
prehending is the the find the seeing of
relations and patterns it's in like
comprehension apprehension pre-ending uh
it's an
idea from ultimately from whitehead uh
it means sort of
getting the the the way you're that
we're sizing things up
mentally mentally getting an optimal
grip on them and so savoring is about
uh making that um a much more flowing
and participatory experience that should
help and because you're doing it outside
the meditation
i'll explain the context um there's less
of a chance of it sort of running away
on its own
so there's going to be that and then
down
the road when we move into the theory of
the neoplatonic part of the course
will be trying to engage in active
imagination and dream work
uh which also will help uh use
imagination to better train perception
but in a very sort of um
disciplined context uh that will
integrate with mindfulness so that
there'll be less of a chance
of there being that sort of runaway
rumination and spiraling
that you're concerned for manual so i
think that
that should help you now perhaps we
could take another question
so mike allison asks a question hi john
i have done your in-person meditation
class a few times
through at uft oh great mike good to see
you again
do you have a week to recommend i go to
catch up
past that point for instance the
chanting is new to me
um so i will find that out and
get it posted in i think it's
i think it's a lesson 11 where we
started
the moving practices we finished prajna
let me quickly check mike and i'll post
it
in the description i'll get a post in
the description for for this video
and that should tell you where what
lessons you can start from
and work your way forward uh and hi
ben uh that is a
a vital presence in the discord server
community and in this sangha
it's always good to see you on ben you
describe
uh prajna
i think you meant prajna as a
non-duality practice
for some non-duality means recognizing
the self as illusory
for me what you teach d centers but
still preserves the self and focuses
on how yourself relates to others um
i i'm actually working on a course right
now ben
and devoting a lot of cognitive
scientific effort to this whole debate
this
there's even a good anthology um edited
by my friend and colleague evan thompson
called self no self
um and part of the uh is that i think um
the presupposition that behind this
debate
that we clearly understand what we mean
when we make this distinction
um i i want to challenge that
presupposition
i think that what the project does
because it's very intense absorption is
you obviously
lose uh the narrative egocentric sense
of self
but if what we mean by self is the
capacity to be here
now sort of heightened sense of design
with some kind of awareness
so an awareness of our here now-ness
and the unity of our experience the
oneness
um if the self is our capacity
for an awareness of that so that
although my mug has the human madness
and it togetherness it doesn't have an
awareness of that
um then i think
that part of the self
um comes to the fore and
things like non-duality practices of
prajna
so often by the way here's just one one
indi
this is not a complete argument well one
indication of what i mean by how people
are slippery about this is they'll say
there's no self
and then what they do is they just shift
functions that have been traditionally
associated to the self
to consciousness and consciousness is
aware
of itself and right and then and that
that doesn't
really answer the problem it just shifts
it around
um so i think there's a lot more
science and philosophy needed
in order to bring clarity conceptual and
theoretical clarity
to this debate and many people are
engaged in it and i'm engaging in it
um and so i want to be careful how i
answer your question
i'm trying to say that i think our
narrative egocentric sense of self
diminishes but the functionality
of an awareness of here now togetherness
what the harder
um i i think that um
is is comes to the fore and even in
traditions that talk about the self as
illusory
like zen you'll hear people talking
about and then you find your true self
and so um like i said i think this is
all very slippery
and what we should do is we should do
two different things
and not confuse them together in the in
the realm of explaining we should do a
lot more cognitive science and
philosophy
and in the realm of training we should
really zero in on the phenomenology
that is actually functional for
transformation for us
and so and then get those two to talk to
each other as much as possible i'm going
to working on that
eventually after i teach this course i'm
going to release
a video series on the nature of the self
i know there's a lot of video series
coming and
they're all and they're all unfolding um
because i'm trying to
i'm trying to be a good teacher for all
of you my job is to
do do a lot of the work because you guys
and
you have your own lives and you don't
have the time i get that
and i'm in a sort of a privileged
position uh but to but how i can
how i can respond to that gift that i've
been given by others
is to be a very good teacher to learn as
much as i can and share that learning
as much as i can as succinctly and as
powerfully as i can for as many of you
as possible and so uh that's what i'm
endeavoring to do
with the help of many other good people
of good faith and good talent gabe
uh we have one more i think um
gabriel rubinstein any tips for
encouraging someone who could
uh benefit from meditation but can't
motivate themselves to do it and there's
resistance to the idea
don't start with the seated practice
get them involved with moving practices
you've seen some of the moving practices
here uh even the tai chi one
like the brush knees i'll talk on on
monday i'm gonna talk to you about
you know the epicurean savoring which
you do while you're walking
um and and then we'll we'll also talk
about
uh philosophical contemplation
contemplative companionships
how you cultivate the philia the
friendship that's at philia sophia which
is central to epicureanism
uh what you can see now is how i how i'm
going to treat the wisdom of my teacher
i'm not going to just teach you what's
in the book i'm going to supplement it
and
expand upon it so there's
back to the original question there's
get them involved in things where
they're moving
uh where they're engaged or what even
practices outside
out in the external world way before you
get them
into uh the acidic practices
everybody um thank you so much for
joining this is always so nourishing for
me
i want to thank my techno friend and my
techno mage
and dear friend amar uh my beloved son
jason
the techno mage apprentice and all the
work he's doing for us
please subscribe to the channel to be
notified of the next video
uh you'll already you'll find the
lecture series awakening for the meeting
crisis
uh the deal logos series uh voices with
raveki
uh very shortly we're going to release
another like another
thing that combines lecture and dialogue
uh greg enriquez and myself are going to
be releasing
uh untangling the world knot of
consciousness uh
dealing with the hard trial problems of
mind and meaning
and you've noted you know that after
socrates is coming um
the god beyond god is coming the nature
of the self is coming
there's a lot that it's coming um invite
others who might benefit
by sharing this series uh please join
the discord servers to chat with others
to do the moving practices with others
to do extra meditation
uh to find a home when uh we three can't
run the sangha also it's gonna be i'm
gonna be coordinating with
uh the discord server because some of
these practices
in the wisdom of my patient need to be
done in groups um
because the western tradition emphasizes
uh
the patterns in your life uh although
there are cited practices
we'll do and so we need to coordinate
that uh i hope to be talking to
mark and brett over at the weekend
reminder we're doing this every weekday
morning at 9 30 eastern time
please follow me on twitter for the
fastest updates
if you don't have any sort of
philosophical opposition to that
please remember continuity of practice
is more important than
quality sorry quantity practice you're
emphasizing
quality in the continuity rather than
just sheer quantity
don't hold yourself to a standard of
perfection
hold yourself to a standard of virtuous
friendship
because there is no enemy worse than
your own
mind and body there's no friend no ally
better
no it's i i can't convey this enough
like when you get that sense of
companionship on the path
that alliance that your own mind and
body
gives you and how that how that's
intermesh
wedded to your inner sage there's no
friendship greater than that
relapsing to yourselves and to each
other
we'll see you all on monday for dharma
day and we'll begin the wisdom of
hypatia
please remember to read the first three
chapters up to page 70. take good care
everyone